Explain in detail:

● HDFS:
• HDFS is Hadoop Distributed File System. The file store in HDFS provides scalable, fault-tolerant storage at low cost.
• The HDFS software detects and compensates for hardware issues, including disk problems and server failure.
• HDFS stores files across the collection of servers in a cluster.
• Files are decomposed into blocks and each block is written to more than one of the servers.
• The replication provides both fault-tolerance and performance.
  HDFS has been designed keeping in view the following features:
• Very large files: Files that are megabytes, gigabytes, terabytes. or petabytes in size.
• Streaming data access: HDFS is built around the idea that data is written once, but read many times.
• A dataset is copied from the source and then analysis is done on that dataset over time.
• Commodity hardware: Hadoop does not require expensive, highly reliable hardware as it is designed to run on clusters of commodity hardware.
 
● Hadoop cluster:
• Data Storage has grown exponentially in the recent past, but data reading speed has not improved radically.
Data Read Speed were:
In 1990, 1400 MB of data having transfer speed as 4.5 MB/s took 5minutes.
In 2010, 1 TB of data having transfer speed as 100 MB/s took 3hours.
But, with Hadoop clusters in the year 2013, 1TB of data in 100 drives took only 2minutes.

● HDFS Blocks:
• Hard Disk has concentric circles which form tracks.
• One file can contain many blocks
• These blocks in a local file system are nearly 512 bytes and are not necessarily continuous.
• For HDFS, since it is designed for large files, block size is 128 MB by default.
• Moreover, it gets blocks of local file system contiguously to minimise head seek time.

First of all, every data block stored in HDFS has its own metadata and needs to be tracked by a central server so that applications needing to access a specific file can be directed to wherever all the file’s blocks are stored. 
If the block size were in the kilobyte range, even modest volumes of data in the terabyte scale would overwhelm the metadata server with too many blocks to track.

Second, HDFS is designed to enable high throughput so that the parallel processing of these large data sets happens as quickly as possible. 
The key to Hadoop’s scalability on the data processing side is, and always will be, parallelism — the ability to process the individual blocks of these large files in parallel.

To enable efficient processing, a balance needs to be struck. 
On one hand, the block size needs to be large enough to warrant the resources dedicated to an individual unit of data processing (for instance, a map or reduce task). 
On the other hand, the block size can’t be so large that the system is waiting a very long time for one last unit of data processing to finish its work.

The above two considerations obviously depend on the kinds of work being done on the data blocks.
